Finding Aid for the Alice Cecilia Cooper Papers LSC.0739
UCLA Library Special Collections
Alice Cecilia Cooper papers
1920-1958
UCLA Library Special Collections
Cooper, Alice Cecilia
LSC.0739
1.0 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Alice Cecilia Cooper (1878-1960) was the supervisor of English for the Oakland Public Schools in Oakland, California. She also taught in Los Angeles schools, San Francisco City College, University of California at Berkeley, and Stanford. The collection consists of Cooper's correspondence with various American and English authors, poets, educators.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Gertrude E. Cooper.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 999645253606533
Biography
Alice Cecilia Cooper born in Walkerton, Canada in 1878; moved to Los Angeles in 1887; received Ph.D. from Stanford; was supervisor of English for the Oakland Public Schools in Oakland, California; in the course of her career, she taught in Los Angeles schools, at San Francisco City College, University of California at Berkeley, and Stanford; published poetry and was author-editor of textbooks and literary anthologies used in schools and universities; died in Los Angeles on June 13, 1960.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of Cooper's correspondence with various American and English authors, poets, educators. The correspondence reflects Cooper's efforts to compile literary anthologies for classroom use while she was Supervisor of English for Oakland Public Schools, Oakland, California. Included in the collection are letters, manuscripts, and ephemera from Edwin Markham, Alfred Noyes, Richard Burton, Walter De La Mare, James Main Dixon, Hamlin Garland, Arthur Guiterman, Louis Untermeyer, Christopher Morley, Will C. Wood, and F.A. Rice.
Expanded Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence of Miss Alice Cooper, Supervisor of English, Oakland Public Schools, with various English and American writers, poets, and educators of the first half of the 20th. century. Most of the letters deal with copyright, giving Miss Cooper permission to include their works in anthologies of modern prose and poetry she was compiling for use as textbooks for Junior High Schools. One of these was published under the joint authorship of Will Christopher Wood, Miss Cooper, and Frederick A. Rice, as America's Message, Boston, New York, etc., Ginn and company, 1925. Of greater note and interest are letters, manuscripts, and ephemera from Edwin Markham, Alfred Noyes, Richard Burton, Walter De La Mare, James Main Dixon, Hamlin Garland, Arthur Guiterman, Louis Untermeyer, and others.
In the collection are also several letters of Will C. Wood and F.A. Rice regarding the Anthology, as well as manuscript poems and ephemera sent to Miss Cooper by her correspondents.
Organization and Arrangement
Collection arranged alphabetically by author.
Authors -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; English -- Study and teaching.; Women educators -- California -- Archives.; Cooper, Alice Cecilia, 1895-1960--Archives.
- Alexander, Hubbard Foster, 1879-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Anderson, Melville Best, 1851-1933., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Arkwright, John Stanhope, 1872-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Armatrong, Hamilton Fish, 1893-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Auslander, Joseph, 1897-., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Barry, Jack., 1 letter (Box 1)
- Bashford, Herbert, 1871-1928., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Bassett, Lee Emerson, 1872-., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Bates, Katherine Lee, 1859-1929., 4 letters. (Box 1)
- Beach, Rex (Ellingwood) 1877-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Bellew, Sir George (Rothe) 1899-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Benet, William Rose, 1886-., 4 letters. (Box 1)
- Bennett, Henry Holcomb, 1863-1924., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Binyon, Laurence, 1869-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Bradley, William Aspenwall, 1878-1939., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Braley, Berton, 1882-., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Branch, Anna Hempstead, 1875-1937., 4 letters. (Box 1)
- Bridges, Robert Seymour, 1844-1930. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  1 letter from Miss Cooper to RSB, and 1 poem of RSB.
- Briggs, Thomas Henry, 1887-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Brown, Alice, 1857-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Brown, Annie Farwell, d. 1927., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Brown, Gilmor, 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Buchan, John, 1875-1940., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Burnet, Dana, 1888-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Burnham, Roger Noble, 1876-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Burr, Amelia Josephine, 1878-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Burton, Richard, 1861-1940., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Butchart, Reuben, 1863-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1962-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Campbell, Mrs., 4 letters. (Box 1)
- Carman, Bliss, 1861-1929., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Chapman, Arthur, 1873-1935., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Chesterton, Gilbert Keith, 1874-1936., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Cheney, John Vance, 1848-1922., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Churchill, Clementine S. (Mrs. Winston Churchill)., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Clarke, Frances Elizabeth., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Clover, Samuel Travers, 1859-1934., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Coates, Mrs. Florence (Earle) 1850-1927., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Cobb, Irvin Shrewsbury, 1876-1944., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Colum, Padraic, 1881-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Conkling, Mrs. Grace Walcott (Hazard) 1878-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Cone, Helen Gray, 1859-1934., 9 letters, and 5 manuscript items (FOLDER). (Box 1)
- Cook, James Henry, 1859-1942., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Coolbright, Ina Donna, 1842-1928., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Crafton, Allen, 1890-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Craig, Alice Evelyn., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Cubberley, Ellwood Patterson, 1868-1941., 1 letter and 1 enclosure. (Box 1)
- Cubberley, Mrs. Helen (Van Uxem)., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Daly, John J., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Daly, Thomas Augustine, 1871-1948., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Darrough, Rose., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Davies, Mary Carolyn., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Davis, Helen Bayley., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Day, Holman Francis, 1865-1935., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- De La Mare, Walter John, 1873-., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Dixon, James Main, 1856-1933., 8 letters. (Box 1)
- Doyle, Sir Arthur Conan, 1859-1930., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Drinkwater, John, 1882-1937., 1 letter and 1 poem. (Box 1)
- Driscoll, Louise, 1875-., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Dumont, Henry., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Eliot, Charles William, 1834-1926., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Faulks, Mrs. Theodosia, 1874-1944., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Garland, Hamlin, 1860-1940., 3 letters. (Box 1)
- Gessler, Clifford, 1893-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Gibson, Wilfrid Wilson, 1878-., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Gifford, Mrs. Fannie Stearns (Davis) 1884-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Gilchrist, Marie Emilie., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Ginn and Company: Publishers., 3 letters. (Box 1)
- Goodhue, Edward Solon, 1861-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Gore-Booth, Eva, 1872-1926., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Gould, Gerald, 1885-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Guiterman, Arthur, 1871-., 5 letters. (Box 1)
- Gray, Agnes Kendrick., 2 letters, and 2 poems (FOLDER). (Box 1)
- Hagedorn, Hermann, 1882-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Hall, Howard Judson, 1869-., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Hazard, Caroline, 1856-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Higginson, Mrs. Ella (Rhoades) 1862-1940., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Hinkson, Mrs. Katherine (Tynan) 1861-1931. (Box 1)
  1 letter to Mrs. Hinkson from Miss Cooper, with Mrs. Hinkson's reply on it.
- Housman, Alfred Edward, 1859-1936., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Hughes, Robert Edward, 1866-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Hughes, Rupert, 1872-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Hulme, Edward Maslin, 1871-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Husband, Joseph, 1885-1938., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Irwin, Wallace, 1895-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Johnston, Oliver Martin, 1866-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Kurtz, Benjamin Putnam, 1877-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Leacock, Stephen Butler, 1869-. (Box 1)
  1 letter to Mr. Leacock from Miss Cooper, with Mr. Leacock's reply on it.
- Leamy, Edmund Stanislaus, 1889-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Le Gallienne, Richard, 1866-., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Leo, Brother, 1881-., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Letts, Winifred M., 1882-., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Loveman, Robert, 1864-1923., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Lowell, Amy, 1874-1925., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- McCarthy, Denis Aloysius, 1871-1931. (Box 1)
  1 letter to Mr. McCarthy from Miss Cooper with Mr. McCarthy's reply on it
- McGaffey, Ernest., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- McGroarty, John Steven, 1862-1944., 3 letters. (Box 1)
- Madden, Captain John, 1878-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Mann, Dorothea Laurence., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Markham, Edwin, 1852-1940., 6 letters, and 15 ephemera (2 FOLDERS). (Box 1)
  (Including copies of his poems).
- Marquis, Don, 1878-1937., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Mifflin, Houston., 6 letters. (Box 1)
- Miller, Joseph Carson, 1883-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Milne, Alan Alexander, 1882-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Minot, John Clair, 1872-1941., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Mitchell, Ernest Pryce, 1862-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Mitchell, Ruth Comfort, 1882-., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Monroe, Harriet, 1860-1936., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Monro, Harold, 1879-1932., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Morley, Christopher Darlington, 1890-., 3 letters. (Box 1)
- Morton, David, 1886-., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Mosher, Raymond Mylar, 1894-., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Murray, Augustus Taber, 1866-1940., 2 letters. (Box 1)
- Murray, John, publisher, London., 1 letter. (Box 1)
- Nesbit, Wilbur Dick. 1871-1927. (Box 2)
  1 letter, and 1 letter from Miss Cooper to Mr. Nesbit, with Mr. Nesbit's reply written at the bottom of it.
- Nicholson, Meredith, 1866-1947., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Noyes, Alfred, 1880-., 3 letters and 6 manuscript items (poems) (FOLDER). (Box 2)
- Odell, Minnie, d. 1940 [pseudonym, Minna Irving]., 2 letters. (Box 2)
- O'Hagan, Thomas, 1855-1939., 8 letters. (Box 2)
- Oxenham, John, pseudonym, d. 1941 [r.n., William A. Dunkerly]., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Paine, Albert Bigelow, 1861-1937., 2 letters. (Box 2)
- Palmer, George Herbert, 1842-1933. (Box 2)
  1 letter to Mr. Palmer from Miss Cooper, with Mr. Palmer's reply on the bottom of it.
- Peabody, Josephine Preston, 1874-1922., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Peck, Samuel Minturn, 1854-1938. (Box 2)
  1 letter from Miss Cooper to Mr. Peck, with Mr. Peck's reply on the bottom of it.
- Phillpotts, Eden, 1862-., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Poole, Luella C., 16 letters and 1 poem (FOLDER). (Box 2)
- Pound, Louise, 1872-., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Powell, Arthur., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Pratt, Harry Noyes, 1879-1944., 5 letters. (Box 2)
- Rawnsley, Mrs. Eleanor Foster (Simpson), 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Reed, Edward Bliss, 1872-1940., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Reese, Lizette Woodworth, 1856-1935., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Rice, Wallace de Groot Cecil, 1859-1939., 3 letters. (Box 2)
- Richards, Mrs. Laura Elizabeth (Howe) 1850-1943., 2 letters. (Box 2)
- Rittenhouse, Jessie Belle, 1869-., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Robinson, Mrs. Corinne (Roosevelt) 1861-1933., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Robinson, Edwin Arlington, 1869-1935., 2 letters. (Box 2)
- Rowan, Andrew Summers, 1857-1943., 3 letters. (Box 2)
- Santayana, George, 1863-1952., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Schauffler, Robert Haven, 1879-., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Scherer, James Augustin Brown, 1870-1944., 3 letters. (Box 2)
- Scollard, Clinton, 1860-1932., 2 letters. (Box 2)
- Shaw, George Bernard, 1856-1950., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Shepard, Odell, 1884-., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Sibley, Robert, 1881-., 2 letters. (Box 2)
- Smith, Francis Scott Key, 1872-., 3 letters. (Box 2)
- Stetson, Mrs. Grace Ellery (Channing) 1862-., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Stoddard, Mrs. Anne (Glen) 1880-., 2 letters. (Box 2)
- Stork, Charles Wharton, 1881-., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Taylor, Mrs. Katherine, 1888-., 2 letters. (Box 2)
- Teasdale, Sara, 1884-1933., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Thomas, Edith Matilda, 1854-1925., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Tietjens, Mrs. Eunice (Hammond) 1884-1944. (Box 2)
  1 letter, and 1 letter from Miss Cooper to Mrs. Tietjens with Mrs. Tietjen's reply on the bottom of it.
- Towne, Charles Hanson, 1877-1949., 2 letters. (Box 2)
- Tupper, Kerr Boyce, 1854-., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Turner, Nancy Byrd, 1880-., 2 letters. (Box 2)
- Untermeyer, Louis, 1885-., 2 letters. (Box 2)
- Van Doren, Carl Clinton, 1885-., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Van Dyke, Henry, 1852-1933., 2 letters. (Box 2)
- Wagner, Harr, 1857-1936., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Warner, Frances Lester, 1888-., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Webb, Margaret E., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Weeks, Edward, 1898-., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Weitbrec, Blanche., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- White, William Allen, 1868-1944., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Wilkinson, Marguerite Ogden (Bigelow) 1883-1928., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Williams, David Rhys., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Woodberry, George Edward, 1855-1930., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Woods, Charles Coke., 1 letter. (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Will C. Wood, 1880-., 6 pieces. (Box 2)
  F.A. Rice with various persons re publication of America's Message.
- Ephemera., 46 pieces. (Box 2)
  Cards, clippings, etc. sent to Miss Cooper by her correspondents.